Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Today's דף *Daf* is מ"ח *Mem-chet*, 48,
and we pick up... I know we rushed the end yesterday, so
I want to spend just a few minutes quickly rereading that.
So let's pick up from the end yesterday from the following. תני
ר' חייא *Tani
Reb Chiya*, the last line of מ"ז עמוד ב' *Mem-zayin amud-bet*. So
we've been talking, we talked about whether ownerless objects are limited to
2,000 אמות amot *Amot*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s framing that as a
debate of ר' יוחנן בן נורי *Reb Yochanan ben Nuri* and the
Rabbis. And now we have this question about whether objects owned by
non-Jews have no limit because their owners don't have any limit of
the תחום techum *Techum*, or whether they also have 2,000 אמות amot
*Amot*, and that's equally debated. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* cited at
the end of yesterday a case about objects brought from outside of
the תחום *Techum* presumably
on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, and that they might be able to
be purchased by the people within the תחום *Techum*. So number one,
what do you mean purchased, it's יום טוב *Yom Tov*, so I
mentioned to you the הלכה halacha. *Halacha* that if you need to
get food for שמחת יום טוב *Simchat Yom Tov*, you can do
a purchase without actually paying the money. And then the question is,
ah, but why are you allowed to move them? Aren't they defined
by a תחום *Techum* or not? And that was the issue, whether
objects owned by a non-Jew are defined by the תחום *Techum*. I
should also mention that beyond all of that, there's a question about...
normally the הלכה *Halacha* is that if a non-Jew brings stuff from
חוץ לתחום chutz ltechum. *Chutz latechum*, forget about moving it because of
תחום *Techum* issues, you're not allowed to benefit from
it because of like when a גוי *Goy* does מלאכה *Melacha* for
you on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat* and יום טוב *Yom Tov* and so
on. So anyway, here presumably you'd have to say that they were
bringing it for no... or for the other people of the city,
the majority of the people not being Jewish. When they do it
for the majority that aren't Jewish, then a Jewish person can benefit
from it. The other important point about that case was that it
said they could, even if they were חוץ לתחום chutz lachum *Chutz
latechum*, they could be carried throughout the city. So רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
and תוספות Tosafot *Tosfot* say it was a city with walls, it
was like being brought into the barn from the first משנה Mishnah,
*Mishna*. But other ראשונים *Rishonim* say no, that if it's even if
it's חוץ לתחום chutz lachum. *Chutz latechum*, any place in the city
is considered the same space. And again, that's a very relevant הלכה
*Halacha* for coming מחוץ לתחום michutz ltechum. *Mechutz latechum*, are you limited
to a walled enclosure or do you have the whole city? מחוץ
לתחום *Mechutz latechum*. Well yes. Okay, correct. Now we pick up from
תני ר' חייא *Tani Reb Chiya*. We'll reread that, we read it
at the end of yesterday, last line of מ"ז עמוד ב' *Mem-zayin
amud-bet*. Where
we won't spend a lot of time with it, but we'll just
take it a little... just reread it. תני ר' חייא *Tani Reb
Chiya*, חרם שבין תחומי שבת Shabbat. *Cherem shebein techumei Shabbat*.
If you have a net that is in the middle of a
river or some body of water that is, that it divides the
תחום שבת Shabbos *Techum Shabbat* of one city and the other city.
צריך מחיצה של ברזל Mechitza Shel Barzel? להפסיקו *Tzarich mechitza shel barzel
lehafshiko*.
So if you want to use the water on one side of
the net or the other, based if you're city A or city
B, you can only do that if there's an iron wall between
it. Why? Because the water is considered to be the water of
the people of the city, and it's not 2,000 אמות amot? *Amot*
from where the water is, but it is based on the people
of the city, so the water, it goes out of תחום *Techum*
as soon as it crosses the net. So how can you use
the water on the other side of the net? It's מחוץ לתחום
*Mechutz latechum*. So you can only do that if you have an
iron wall. מחייך עליה ר' יוסי בר' חנינא *Mechayech alei Reb Yose
bar Reb Chanina*. So ר' יוסי בר' חנינא *Reb Yose bar Reb
Chanina* laughed on this, מקדטי *Mokdeti*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
מאי טעמא קמחייך *Mai taama kamechayech*? Why are you laughing? אילימא משום
דתני לה כרבי יוחנן בן נורי לחומרא *Ilei'ma mishum de-tani la kerabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri le-chumra*. If it's because he holds like ר' יוחנן
בן נורי *Reb Yochanan ben Nuri* and he's being strict, meaning that
this is sort of like חפצי הפקר Cheftzei Hefker, *Chefzei hefker*, and
therefore he's being strict to treat חפצי הפקר *Chefzei hefker* as limited
by a תחום *Techum*, ואיהו סבירא ליה כרבנן לקולא *Ve-ihu sevira lei
kerabnan lekula*, and he holds like the Rabbis לקולא *Lekula* that חפצי
הפקר *Chefzei hefker* aren't limited. ומשום דסבר לקולא *Umishum desavar lekula*, just
because you are lenient, מאן דתני לחומרא מחייך עליה *Man detani lechumra
mechayech alei*? Somebody who's going to be strict, you're going to mock
them? That's a legitimate position. So I should just stop by noting
two things. First of all, although we said הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב
*Halacha kedivrei hameikel be-eruv*, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* here clearly feels that
not everybody has to buy into that. You know, that was not
said as a דברי הכל *Divrei hakol*, it was one opinion that
כל הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב *Kol halacha kedivrei hameikel be-eruv*. So you
see here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not assuming that everybody has
to agree to that. Number two, it's a little bit unclear why
this is dependent on the issue of ר' יוחנן בן נורי *Reb
Yochanan ben Nuri* and the Rabbis of חפצי הפקר *Chefzei hefker*. Because
if it was חפצי הפקר *Chefzei hefker*, then it should not be
defined by the people of the city. It should be 2,000 אמות
amot *Amot* from where the water is, not 2,000 אמות amot *Amot*
from where the people of the city are. So it's in this
weird middle space that technically it's ownerless, but that the people of
the city want to use it, and somehow that allows it to
or makes it defined by the people of the city. But again,
it's a little bit strange because if it was the real הלכה
*Halacha* of חפצי הפקר *Chefzei hefker*, it would be its own 2,000
אמות amot, *Amot*, not the 2,000 אמות amot. *Amot* of the city.
But anyway, that's how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* frames it, it's חפצי
הפקר *Chefzei hefker*. So what if he's being strict and limiting it
by the 2,000 אמות amot *Amot* of the city? Why is that
a reason to mock? אלא Ela, משום דתניא Detanya, *Ella mishum detanya*,
here's why he was mocking it. Because I don't care if it's
חפצי הפקר *Chefzei hefker*, not חפצי הפקר *Chefzei hefker*, they should never
have a תחום *Techum*. Why?
Because we taught in the ברייתא, Braisa נהרות המושכין ומעיינות הנובעים, Neharos
hamoshchin umayanos hanovim, if you have a flowing river and other sort
of bodies of water, הרי הן כרגלי כל אדם, Harei hen keraglei
kol adam,
they are whoever, anybody can use them and they're not limited because
they never קנו שביתה. kanu shvisa. So this should be the same.
So the גמרא Gemara says, again treating them as if they're חפצי
הפקר, not owned by the people of the city. So the גמרא
Gemara says, ודילמא במכונסים, Udilma bimchunasim,
why is that a reason to mock? Maybe this body of water
was stationary, was not flowing? Now, of course the answer could be
no, it actually was a flowing body of water, but the גמרא
Gemara is somehow saying, how do you know, maybe it was a
stationary body of water? אלא, Ela,
because the reason is that it doesn't, because the statement was not
about a particular body, it was an abstract statement. רבי חייא, Rabbi
Chiyya, it says רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya says חירים שבין תחומי שבת.
Cheirim shebein techumei Shabbos.
So since he did not, he wasn't speaking about a specific body
of water, why would you mock? Maybe this statement was made in
reference to a stationary body of water? Okay, so here's the גמרא.
Gemara If it's a stationary body of water and it is קונה
שביתה koneh shvisa and it is limited by 2000 אמות amot, of
the city, then רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya is right that there's a
real problem here. How could one side use the other side? The
water is going חוץ לתחום. So it's a reasonable position. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אלא, Ela, here's why it was being mocked. משום
דקתני צריך מחיצה של ברזל להפסיקו, Mishum dektani tzarich mechitzah shel barzel
lehafshiko,
because he thinks that I hear that you could say it's a
problem, I don't get why you think you have a solution. How
does an iron wall make it any better? ומאי שנא קנים דלא,
Umai shena kanim dlo,
why are you assuming that a reed wall would not be good
enough? Presumably this netting, why is this netting not good enough? דאיילי
בהו מיא, De'ayli behu maya,
because the water passes through it, so what good does the wall
do if water passes through it? Okay, and then you're having water
that went מחוץ לתחום. So he says, if that's your problem, של
ברזל נמי איילי בהו מיא, Shel barzel nami ayli behu maya,
even if it's an iron wall, the water passes through it. Now
not literally through it, but under it. We're assuming you don't mean
a wall having going all the way to the bottom of the
floor of the lake or whatever it is. So we mean a
10 טפח tefach wall. So he's saying, look, he was mocking it.
If you really think you've got a problem, a 10 טפח tefach
iron wall isn't going to solve it. It's no better than a
netting. And that was his issue. So the גמרא Gemara says, ודילמא,
Udilma, okay,
but maybe his point was צריכה ואין לה תקנה קאמר. Tzricha ve'ein
lah takanah ka'amar.
Maybe his point was exactly that, was to make like a hyperbole
and saying if you wanted to fix this, you would need an
iron wall that would go all the way to the bottom and
stop the water. And he wasn't really suggesting a solution. Maybe it
was his way of articulating that there's no solution. You can't use
the water. So good, that's a reasonable position. Why are you mocking
it? So אלא, here's why he's mocking it. That even if I
buy in that this is a problem, use that water from one
side to the other side, משום דקלושי הקילו חכמים במים. Mishum de'kalushei
hikelu chachamim bemayim. We know that the sages were lenient when it
comes to bodies of water and in order to enable people to
use the water, allowed it to be considered like there really was
a wall even though it normally would not satisfy the criteria of
a wall. What is the classic case about that? You're on a
boat, you want to draw water from the ocean. Okay, it's a
problem cause you're taking from the ocean which is a כרמלית karmelis
or whatever it is and your boat's a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
So what you do is before שבת, you create a little like
box on the side of the boat with no floor and you
lower the bucket through the box. Now why does that work and
over off the side? Because it's that box which has four walls
is seen as going all the way down to the floor of
the ocean and makes it a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. But the
problem is that normally a מחיצה mechitzah that's off the ground doesn't
count as a מחיצה. mechitzah. And the answer is it's a special
leniency regarding water, bodies of water, to allow you to use the
water and so on and have that מחיצה mechitzah work. So if
we can say that, that that מחיצה mechitzah goes down through the
water to the floor even though halachically it shouldn't work, so here
too this netting, it should be considered even if I admit to
your problem, it should be considered as a wall. It doesn't matter
that there are holes in it and as going to the ground.
And I don't understand why you have this whole issue with an
iron wall. Iron wall is no better than the netting and actually
the netting should be just fine because we're dealing with bodies of
water and we make these types of leniencies. So that's what it
says, אלא משום דקלושי הקילו חכמים במים, Ela mishum de'kalushei hikelu chachamim
bemayim, כדרבי טבלא. Kederabbi Tavla. Like רבי טבלא. Rabbi Tavla. דבעי
מיניה רבי טבלא
מרב, Debaei minei Rabbi Tavla me'Rav, רבי טבלא Rabbi Tavla asked רב,
Rav, מחיצה תלויה מהו שתתיר בחורבה. Mechitzah teluyah mahu shetatir bechurbah. But
this suspended wall off the side of the boat, would that work
on dry land? ואמר ליה, Ve'amar lei, he said to him, אין
מחיצה תלויה מתרת אלא במים. Ein mechitzah teluyah materes ela bemayim. No,
I'm sorry, this suspended wall only works in water. קלושי הקילו חכמים
במים, Kalushei hikelu chachamim bemayim,
it's a special leniency by water and here too he said even
if I admit that this is a problem, the netting should be
a sufficient solution. Charlie, you had a question?
Yeah, well there's a general question.
Secular laws there are very complicated and obscure rules regarding water rights.
Aha. And we're talking about water that's flowing versus water that's not.
So how is there similar and it differs in very in different
parts of the United States. In our legal system do we have
that kind of water rights?
You mean less about private and more about like the rights of
a country and the water rights of a country?
That includes includes individuals like if they
how much water can I take from the Hudson River without returning
it? How much water can I take from the Colorado River without
returning it?
Yeah, you know, I don't know yeah I don't know about detailed
issues there. There's a whole discussion that the גמרא בגיטין Gemara in
Gittin has about sort of the Mediterranean, how much of the coast
of the Mediterranean is considered to be part of ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael as opposed to how much is considered, you know, international waters.
That's actually another part of the law. That's more for like הלכות
התלויות בארץ, Hilchos Hatluyos Ba'aretz, but in terms of your sort of
ownership issues and so on, not that comes to mind. I mean,
there's a lot of discussion about wells of different, you know, of
one city and wells of another city, but not the same I
think in terms of what you're talking about. Yes.
So then
why was the suggestion the מחיצה mechitza של ברזל?
I have no idea. Okay, חכמים, Chachamim, maybe it meant all the
way to the floor, I don't know. וחכמים אומרים אין לו אלא
ארבע. Vechachamim Omrim Ein Lo Ela Arba. Now we get back, now
it's actually we get back to the משנה, Mishnah and this is
the question about when you are stuck with your four אמות amot
because you went חוץ לתחום or you fell asleep and according to
the position you weren't קונה שביתה. koneh shevita. How do you measure
the four אמות? amot So the חכמים Chachamim say four אמות amot
and then and then you have, I'm sorry, you have the position
of who was it? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that said you only
have two אמות amot. in every in any direction. And the חכמים
Chachamim say no, you have four אמות, amot but once you pick
a side, you're stuck to it. So meaning everybody agrees according to
that that you have a box that's four by four אמות. amot
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you are always defined as the middle
of the box, but חכמים Chachamim are saying you can define where
you start in that box. You can say you have one אמה
ama behind you and three in front of you, you have two
and two, you have four אמות amot in front of you, zero
behind you, so everybody agrees you've got the box, the question is
where do you start? And it's actually quite interesting that the חכמים
Chachamim allow for such subjectivity, normally we like things to be always
the same. So that's the debate. So the גמרא Gemara says רבי
יהודה היינו תנא קמא. Rabbi Yehuda Hainu Tanna Kama. So when so
the חכמים Chachamim first said four אמות, amot then רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer said two אמות amot in each direction, and then רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda said, no, four אמות amot. but you get to pick
which side. So the גמרא Gemara says, isn't רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
who says four אמות amot, the same as the תנא קמא? Tanna
Kama? The משנה Mishnah began by saying four אמות. amot אמר רבא
שמונה על שמונה איכא בינייהו. Amar Rava Shmona Al Shmona Ika Beinaihu.
Ah, the first opinion that said four אמות amot actually is much
more lenient. The first opinion is four אמות amot in each direction.
The same way we say two thousand אמות amot in each direction,
so when we give a number we mean in each direction. The
first opinion that said four אמות amot means four אמות amot in
each direction, which is a box of eight by eight אמות. amot.
So it first starts by saying you've got four אמות, amot which
implicitly means four אמות amot, in each direction, then רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says no, two אמות amot in each direction, you're in the
middle of a four by four box, and then רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says I agree to the four by four box, but you
get to decide where you start. But the first position is much
more lenient, it's you're in the middle of an eight by eight
box. Okay, you have four אמות amot. in each direction. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, תניא נמי הכי, Tanya Nami Hachi,
we taught similar, יש לו שמונה על שמונה דברי רבי מאיר. Yesh
Lo Shmona Al Shmona Divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who
isn't mentioned in our משנה Mishna, but is often the סתם Stam
voice in the ברייתא Braisa, says explicitly, you have eight you're in
a middle of an eight by eight box. ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava,
now רבא Rava says, מחלוקת להלך. Machlokes Lehalech. That issue of do
you have four אמות amot in each direction, are you in an
eight by eight box or a four by four box, that's about
moving, you know, if you're חוץ לתחום. אבל לטלטל, Aval Letaltel, carrying,
like you cannot carry in a רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. So דברי
הכל ארבע אמות אין טפי לא. Divrei Hakol Arba Amos In Tfei
Lo. Nobody would say, even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say that
you cannot, you know, if let's say here I was, I was
in the middle of my here I am, I'm in the you
know, I'm in the middle of my four by four box. Here
I am according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, I have four אמות
amot. this way, four אמות amot. that way. I can't go to
this side, pick up an object, and then carry it all the
way back to the other side, right, and carry the object eight
אמות. amot, Okay? Everybody agrees that carrying in רשות הרבים Reshus Harabim
is limited to four אמות amot. from where I picked up the
object. So even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says a box of
eight אמות, amot, that's for walking, that is not for carrying. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, so והני ארבע אמות היכא
כתיבא? Ve'hani Arba Amos Hecha Ksiva? Where are these four אמות amot
written? Meaning, why is it okay, they might debate how, you know,
are you in the is it four in each direction? Are you
in the middle of the box? Are you at the edge of
the box? But everybody agrees to the idea of four אמות. amot,
Where is it you know, what's it based on? Where is it
written in the פסוק? pasuk? מאלפיים אמת התחום? Mi'alpayim Amas Hatchum? Okay,
so it's interesting, the גמרא Gemara hasn't asked that yet. I know,
כדתניא, kidtanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa. שבו איש. Shevu Ish.
It also had an answer it wanted to give. שבו איש תחתיו
shvu ish tachtav *shevu ish tachtav*. Okay, every person should sit in
his place, which is how we learn like the idea of not
traveling outside of city limits, whether it's דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* or דרבנן *d'Rabanan*,
but anyway, איש *ish* person sit in his place, כתחתיו *ke-tachtav*, like
the space underneath you. Now, it does not mean literally where your
feet are standing, that is not four by four, or even where
you'd be sitting if you were sitting, but it means if you
were completely let's say lying down. Okay, וכמה תחתיו *ve-chama tachtav*, how
much is the space underneath you? גופו שלוש אמות amot *gufo shalosh
amot*. So your body is שלוש אמות amot *shalosh amot*, I'll get
back to that in a minute, ואמה *ve-amah* plus an additional אמה
amah, *amah* כדי לפשוט ידיו ורגליו *kedei lifshot yadav ve-raglav*, because if
you are sleeping, you know, you stretch out and you whatever, so
that extra, you know, so the space for your arms or whatever,
that gives you an extra אמה amah *amah*. דברי רבי מאיר *Divrei
Rabi Meir*, that's what רבי מאיר *Rabi Meir* says. I'm sorry, I
skipped a line. No, דברי רבי מאיר *Divrei Rabi Meir*, that's right.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, אומר *Rabi Yehuda omer*, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rabi Yehuda* agrees, except he just describes it a little differently. גופו
שלוש אמות amot *gufo shalosh amot*, your
body is שלוש אמות amot *shalosh amot*, ואמה *ve-amah* and the extra
אמה amah.
*amah* כדי שיטול חפץ מתחת מרגלותיו ומניח תחת מראשותיו *kedei she-yitol chefetz
mi-tachas margelosav u-maniach tachas merashosav*. Take something from underneath your feet and
put it underneath your head. So it's not exactly clear what that
extra because the object is goes below your feet that you need,
maybe it's a pillow, a little bit above your head, and that
gives you ארבע אמות amot *arba amot*. By the way, you know,
this idea of lying down on the ground and take an object
underneath your head, very much evokes the whole יעקב *Yaakov* story. I
don't know if that's intentional, but it's interesting, the first one you're
talking about lying down and then something under your head, anyway, okay.
מאי בינייהו *mai beinaiu*, what's the difference? They both agree to ארבע
אמות amot *arba amot*. איכא בינייהו ארבע אמות amot. מצומצמות *ika beinaiu
arba amot metzumtzamot*. If it's precisely ארבע אמות amot. *arba amot* or
like maybe measured a little more loosely because apparently רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says if it's the issue of stretching, that would give you a
little bit of like a little more. And you know, there're different
ways, there're different ways of measuring, you know, there're different אמות *amot*.
There's an אמה amah. *amah* with different sort of, you know, degrees
of error or whatever, you know, or buffer. You know, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* talks about different measuring things, sticks that they had in
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*, whether also whether you hold
your hand the fingers are tight or the fingers are loose, right,
שוחקות *sochokot*, you know, or, you know, or אצבעות *atzbaot* the גמרא
gemara *Gemara* had before. So anyway, there're slightly different measurements. Now, I
want to say something about a person being שלוש אמות *shalosh amot*.
So how big is שלוש אמות *shalosh amot*? So how big is
an אמה amah. *amah*? So it depends who you ask. רב חיים
נאה Rav Chaim Na'eh *Rav Chaim Na'eh*, who by now I think
almost everybody accepts his measurements because, you know, he did the most,
you know, thorough and rigorous analysis of all of the issues around
the אמה amah. *amah* plus everything he figured out was supported by
archaeological findings. Particularly the archaeological findings that are most significant is the
or some of it some that are most significant are the מקואות
*mikvaos* at מצדה *Masada*. Because they had very little water at מצדה
*Masada*. So the assumption is that those מקואות *mikvaos* would not be
any bigger than they had to be, okay, and the size of
a מקוה *mikvah* is שלוש אמות *shalosh amot* by אמה *amah*, and
actually when, you know, that exactly corresponded to the measurements of רב
Rav חיים נאה *Rav Chaim Na'eh*, so his are pretty much, you
know, some people are מחמיר machmir *machmir* for bigger measurements, but, you
know, most people will agree that those are the most accurate measurements.
So according to him, an אמה *amah* is about a foot and
a half. A טפח *tefach* is about three inches, a little more,
I forget exactly, 3.1, 3.2, so you multiply it by six, about
18-19 inches. A little bit more maybe a little bit more than
a foot and a half. Okay, so שלוש אמות *shalosh amot* is
four and a half feet. Now, it is true people were shorter
back then. But not that much shorter. We're not talking about the
Paleolithic period or something. Okay, so what's four and a half feet
talking about? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says, he doesn't start with that
question, but he starts with the following question. תוספות Tosefos *Tosafos* says
in the גמרא gemara. *Gemara* in בבא בתרא *Bava Basra*, when it
talks about making a wall between different, you know, yards and you're
doing it for היזק ראייה *hezek re'iyah*, for privacy purposes so you
can't see from one yard to the next, it says that it
has to be ארבע אמות *arba amot*. Why does it have to
be ארבע אמות *arba amot* if this גמרא gemara *Gemara* is saying
people are only שלוש אמות *shalosh amot*? So תוספות Tosefos *Tosafos*'s first
answer is we're afraid that you might stand on your tippy-toes in
order to look at the other guy, what's going on in the
other guy's backyard. So that's a great little answer. I just want
to show you how the words he uses to describe standing on
your tippy-toes is, he says ופעמים נמי *u-pe'amim nami*, this is in
the גופו *gufo* like four lines in, ופעמים נמי *u-pe'amim nami* says
שמגביה עקיבו *she-magbi'a akeivo*, you lift up your heel, ועומד על אצבעות
רגליו *ve-omed al etzbeos raglav*, and you stand on your toes. So,
you know, we have to keep the wall higher for prying eyes.
But then he says, no, actually the real answer says תוספות *Tosafos*
is that שלוש אמות *shalosh amot* is till your shoulders, till your
head. Plus your head is about another אמה *amah*. Now, that's funny
because then why didn't the גמרא gemara *Gemara* say that for ארבע
אמות *arba amot*? Why did they have to do the whole thing
מתחת מראשותיו *mi-tachas merashosav*? But תוספות *Tosafos* says, you know, because people
normally don't lie totally flat out, they curl a little bit. It's
also a problem because the size of a מקוה *mikvah* is שלוש
אמות *shalosh amot* by אמה *amah* and that's supposed to be the
size for a person. So תוספות *Tosafos* also says, well, when you
go in the water, you know, you crouch down a little bit.
But there is this little problem that the simple sense of the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* sounds like the full height of a person is
שלוש אמות *shalosh amot*, but it doesn't work in current terms. how
we measure an אמה and it doesn't work in terms of some
other sources. So it's generally what's accepted is תוספות'ס Tosefot's interpretation, which
is three אמות till shoulder height plus your head. So four and
a half feet till shoulder height for Jews, that's probably about accurate.
Yes. Well you mentioned leniency, but with your leniencies create stringencies and
vice versa. So you can have a shorter מחיצה with a smaller
אמה, but you also have less distance you can travel on שבת.
Right, that's true. So there are yeah so there are all those
consequences. Some people might be מחמיר machmir all the in all directions
all the time, but רב חיים נאה is basically accepted as you
know as as the base. תוספות also points out that the size
of the of the what are those called? The כוכין kuchin is
the Hebrew word but the the niches in the wall of a
cave that they bury people in, catacombs? No, but what's the niche
called? Is there a word for the niche? Anyway, the גמרא Gemara
says that that length is four אמות. So now of course you're
all you know so תוספות says you see that with the head
it's four אמות. Yes, רב Goldin, is this whole issue still not
totally clear and the rabbis went ahead and permitting us to make
עירובים eruvs they're really violating what the תורה Torah says? I know
the תורה... Torah... Well, yes, yes. But of course the simple sense
of the פסוקים psukim though is in the context of the מן,
mahn, right? It's not that absolute you can't move, it's like don't
go out and search for the מן. mahn. I understand. So they're
striking the balance, learning from the פסוק pasuk but describing it very
broadly. Taken away from it but but we're not... I know, which
is why it's more of an אסמכתא. asmachta. But you're right. If
you want, you know, look, what people another example, another example of
the rabbis really abrogating... Reinterpreting it. No, if you feel that it's
really biblical law, then you're making a radical change in the פשט.
pshat. But they felt that this was they they you know the
dominant position was is that that's not what the פסוק pasuk means
and the whole issue, it's all an אסמכתא. asmachta. And I don't
think that but I do think the larger point being that people
don't appreciate that of the different sects and flavors of Judaism that
was around at that time, חז"ל Chazal were by far the most
lenient. You know vis-à-vis the פרושים Perushim and the צדוקים Tzadukim you
know I mean no they were vis-à-vis the צדוקים Tzadukim and the
Essenes and whatever. Correct, correct. Okay, so let's go further. So now
it says like this. Okay. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר ליה רב משרשיא Amar lei Rav Mesharsheya so רב משרשיא
Rav Mesharsheya said לבריה livreih to his son: כי אזלת לקמי דרב
פפא, Ki azlat lekamei d'Rav Papa, when you go to see רב
פפא, Rav Papa, you know he was maybe going to learn there
at the ישיבה yeshiva whatever, anyway when you go see רב פפא,
Rav Papa, בעי מיניה, baei minei, ask from him the following איבעיא.
ibeiya. ארבע אמות שאמרו, Arba amot she'amru, when they say a person
has four אמות, whether four in each direction, a total of four
by four, באמה דידיה יהבינן ליה? ba'amah didey havina lei? Do we
measure it with... subjectively? Because it's based on שבו איש תחתיו which
is like your space, and if it's an idea based on the
פסוק pasuk and conceptually an idea of your space, then maybe we
should measure it in your אמות. So if you're like five or
six, right? You don't mean by you, if you're really big, then
you're really small? Yes, yes. So the question is that if you're
big and you have long arms, so your four אמות, you know
an אמה is from the elbow to the top of your middle
finger, so we should measure it in your four אמות and you
should get more space because your space is more, you're a big
guy. Or less if you're a small guy. Okay, so do we
measure it באמה דידיה יהבינן ליה ba'amah didey havina lei או באמה
של קודש יהבינן ליה? o ba'amah shel kodesh havina lei? Or by
the standard אמה. It says אמה של קודש amah shel kodesh because
they kept the you know the measuring sticks in the בית המקדש.
Beit Hamikdash So there were they were different measuring sticks that they
used for when building the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash, and that was
like, you know my father used to work at the National Bureau
of Standards, which is now called the National Institute of Science and
Technology and they had there like encased in glass the official measurement
of no of a meter and it was like what was it
made in like something like gold or some type of a metal.
It's an alloy that does not contract and like that was the
measurement of a meter for כל העולם כולו. kol ha'olam kulo. So
this was the same thing, they had it in the בית המקדש,
the official measurement of an אמה. So that's the way of referring
to a standard אמה. And a foot is actually legally defined in
terms of meters at 30.48 centimeters. Oh very interesting. Okay, so alright,
so he says, אם אמר לך, im amar lach, if he tells
you אמה של קודש יהבינן ליה amah shel kodesh havina lei that
we do standardized אמות, so עוג מלך הבשן מה תהא עליו? Og
Melech HaBashan matei lei? So let's say you happen to have עוג
Og who converted and he's trying to keep שבת and he only
has four אמות for him for him four אמות he can't even
move his foot. So you know obviously so anyway it's a little
bit of a reductio ad absurdum but the point being that if
the idea is to give a guy space to move around maybe
you have to be more flexible based on the size of the
person. Okay, ואם אמר לך באמה דידיה יהבינן ליה, ve'im amar lach
ba'amah didey havina lei, and if he tells you fine we'll measure
it with the person's that person's own אמה. אימא ליה *Eima leh*,
say to him, if that's true, מאי טעמא לא תניא לגבי יש
אמה לכל לפי מה שהוא אדם *mai ta'ama lo tanya legabei yesh
amah lechol lefi ma she'hu adam*? We have a משנה *mishnah* in
כלים kelim *Kelim* that says a list of things that you measure
based on the individual person and not by a standard measurement. Like
when the כהן *kohen* takes for the מנחה *mincha* the קומץ *kometz*,
how big is a קומץ *kometz*, it goes by the individual כהן
*kohen*. When he takes for burning the קטורת *ketoret* on יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur* מלא חפניו *melo chofnav*, right, his two scoops of both
his hands, it doesn't go by a standard measure, it goes by
the individual כהן *kohen*. So that משנה *mishnah* there lists things that
go by the individual. So why didn't it mention the four אמות
*amot* if this is really subjective? So if it's subjective it should
have been in the list. And if it's an objective four אמה
*amah* measurement, then it's not fair to big people. So what's the
הלכה *halacha*? Is it just talking about ritual things in the בית
המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*? Oh no, not just ritual in the בית המקדש
*Beis Hamikdash*, the whole list of things. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* says okay, so that's what you should ask רב פפא *Rav
Pappa*. Okay. כי אתא לקמיה דרב פפא *Ki ata lekamei deRav Pappa*,
so he came to רב פפא *Rav Pappa*, אמר amar, ליה *amar
leh* and רב פפא *Rav Pappa* said back to him, אדדייקינן כולי
האי לא הוי תנינן *iddaykinan kulei hai lo havei taninan*. If we
would spend all of our time, you know, asking these types of
questions, we would never get any learning done. Anyway, so it's not
exactly clear what bothered him so much, but apparently, as we'll see
from his answer, let's see his answer and then I'll tell you
back how some people explain what that response meant. לעולם באמה דידיה
יהבינן ליה *Le'olam be'amah didei yahavinan leh*, which is a surprising answer
because it's very rare that we do subjective measurements. So actually we
do the person's measurements, you make a good point that if it's
a big guy we gotta give him more space. ודקא קשיא kashya,
לך מאי טעמא לא תניא גבי יש אמרו *Vedaka kashya lach mai
ta'ama lo tanya gabei yesh ameru*, why is it not in that
list over there in כלים kelim *Kelim* of things that go by
the individual person? דלא פסיקא ליה *delo pesika leh*, because it's not
always true. Why is it not always true? משום דאיכא ננס באיבריו
*Mishum de'ika nanas be'eivarav*. You could have a guy that has foreshortened
limbs. Not ננס *nanas* a midget, presumably the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* would
say if he's a small guy maybe we do give him less
because it's all about giving you space to move around. But let's
say you have disproportionate limbs. Let's say you're a really big guy
but you have short arms. So then if we give you your
four אמות *amot* measured by your arm, we're actually giving you less
space than is appropriate. So for that type of a person, we
would give a standard four אמות *amot*. אמה של הקדש *amah shel
hechdesh*. So we give you a subjective one presumably if it's more
lenient, if you're a big guy. It's not clear what we would
give you if you're totally a small guy, maybe it would also
be smaller. But if somehow it doesn't make sense, there's some disproportion
going on, then we would give you the standard four אמות *amot*.
אמה של הקדש *amah shel hechdesh*. So anyway, some say that his
reason of saying like, you know, if we would ask those types
of questions, the word דייק *dayek* often means to learn something from
the precise formulation of the text. So here he's saying your question
was not based on how the text was written, your question was
based on the fact that something was missing from a list. You
said if it were subjective it should have been on a list.
That's not a real good דיוק *diyuk* because there's a lot of
reasons why things might not be on a list. So that's some
want to say that's why he was responding like you know you're
spending too much time on the questions, it shouldn't bother you so
much why something isn't on a list, there could be other reasons.
One minute, first over to the question then I'm gonna go... what?
Yes, so maybe this is related to the idea we had before,
if you don't know where the תחום *techum* is then you pace
two thousand paces. Aha, it's just the same type of thing that's
a subjective, not just an exigency but maybe that's actual, maybe it's
the same thing, it's by your אמות *amot* or by your... Yeah,
except that none of the פוסקים *poskim* say that, they say that's
only if you don't know. Meaning if I actually am a big
guy and we've measured the two thousand אמות *amot* and I know
that my paces are bigger, nobody says I get more, I get
more. Well that was gonna be my first question, should it be...
No, so that's never raised. Yeah, that's never raised. Here the emphasis
seems to be that the idea four אמות *amot* first of all
it's learned from the word תחתיו *tachtav*, which is very subjective, your
space. And also it seems to be as opposed to two thousand
אמות *amot* that you know you can't make a guy stand stock
still the entire שבת *Shabbos*. You need a certain amount of space
to move around. So there there seems to be like almost like
an injustice if you're a huge guy and to squeeze you into
a small box, that seems to be what bothers the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. The two thousand אמות *amot* you're right, you can use your
pace as an estimate but nobody ever says that's the actual measurement.
Rivka? I'm just a reality check. If someone is in the desert
somewhere, they really expect a person to be stuck for twenty-four hours
not to move... I mean I know, it's a little crazy. I
mean look, the idea four אמות *amot* is you can just sit
down and lie down and hang out there. Now of course you
remember the משנה *mishnah* at the beginning did say, you know, you
remember the משנה *mishnah* at the beginning did say if you have
to go to the bathroom you can go out of there and
if you happen to find a space within the תחום *techum*, you
know, then you're back into the תחום *techum* but that's assuming that
you left against your will. If you willfully violated it and left
you really are stuck. But I think it's important to clarify... I
know, it's important... It's important that you raise the question. Look, because
it is true, it's possible to do, you can just lie down
and take a long nap for all of שבת, not impossible, but
it is hard to imagine that somebody could abide by this. You
are correct. Which is why I think again, the גמרא Gemara before
gave you some outs about walking, go to the bathroom and walking
back, but that didn't work in all cases. I think that the
reality check is a good one. I don't know how people would
actually do it. All right, so let's see now as the גמרא
Gemara, continues, הא משניא מקצת אמותיו של זה. He mishnaya miktzat amotav
shel zeh. So the גמרא then, the next case in the משנה,
if you'll remember, said if you have two people whose four אמות
overlap, then they can bring stuff and use stuff in the overlapping
space, because they're moving within each other's space, it's okay. But they
can't go to sort of the spaces at the edge because, if
these are the two people, they can use the space in between
them if it's overlapping space, but the space behind them, right, the
external space, two people, right, the space behind them, I, this guy
can't use the space behind him because it's outside of his four
אמות and vice versa. Okay, so you can't even walk there, let
alone use it. Okay, so then you have two people at a
chart. Right, well, that's what the גמרא said. And then it came
to the case of, it said, that is similar like if you
had cases of three people, right? So it says, so it says
first you have this case, and it says this guy's four אמות
is like this, this guy's is like this, and this guy's is
like this. So this guy can use shared space here and shared
space here, but these two, obviously this guy cannot go ahead and
even walk into let alone take stuff out of that space. And
then it says, what's that similar to? It's similar to three courtyards
that are open one to another and open to the רשות הרבים.
reshut harabim. Okay, and I'll say in a minute why it's important
that they're open to the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Three courtyards, and
here's the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Again, and if these two made
an עירוב eruv and these two made an עירוב, eruv, so same
story, these two can use all of this space, these two can
use all of this space. So the middle guy can use any
space and so on, but this guy can't use his space because
there's no עירוב eruv from the outer extremities. The reason it has
to be open to רשות הרבים reshut harabim is because if it
wasn't, if you had a case like this, and we'll see this
later, if this was the street, okay, and the courtyards were like
this, and it wasn't that all of them were open to רשות
הרבים, reshut harabim, it was only one of them, and to get
to the back courtyard you had to go through the others, then
you cannot make, in some ways we'll worry about the details later,
you cannot make independent עירובין eruvin because they're not stand-alone. You know,
they necessarily are, this courtyard necessarily relates to people in the outer
courtyards. Okay, so that's why it says that it opens to רשות
הרבים reshut harabim so you don't have to worry about that case.
Yes. So what if you had your four אמות square and you
have two people both standing right in the middle of it? And
so supposedly had the same four אמות. They have the same four,
yeah. But they have to choose a direction and one of them
chooses this direction... According to the, according to רבי יהודה, that you
choose which direction. Let's say the other one goes another direction. He
goes along the hypotenuse, which would be longer than the four... No,
that's a good point. You don't... well, you mean... and who defines
it first? Right? But each person gets to define his four אמות.
In your case, if this guy wanted to say... this is according
to רבי יהודה that says you pick where you are in the
box. So if this one wanted to do this and this one
wanted to do that, it's true that if he sort of did
it like this, you know, he could go further down here, but
it would have consequences, you know, where you are in the box.
Okay, let's take a look now as the גמרא continues. למה לי
למימר, Lameleh lemeimar, האי משנה מקצת אמותיו של זה. Hai mishna miktzat
amotav shel zeh. למה לי למימר למה דבר דומה? Lameleh lemeimar lema
davar domeh? Why does it have to say oh, this is just
like the courtyard case? You know, what was difficult about that issue
that you had to bring in the courtyard case? The courtyard case
actually is more complicated as we're going to see in a few
minutes. So, הכי קאמר ליה רבי שמעון לרבנן. Hachi kamer leh Rabbi
Shimon leRabbanan. And here's the point. Because we're about to see in
the courtyard case that while רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, like we
saw, that the middle can do with the outer, but the outer
can't do with one another, we're going to see in a minute
that the רבנן Rabbanan say none of them can do it. In
this case of the courtyards here, none of them can move into
anybody else's space, it doesn't work. Okay, and we'll see why in
a minute. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying to the רבנן
Rabbanan is why do you argue with me in the courtyard case?
It should be just like the people case where you agree with
me. So הכי קאמר ליה רבי שמעון לרבנן. Hachi kamer leh Rabbi
Shimon leRabbanan. מכדי, Mikdi, let's take a look. למה דבר דומה לשלוש
חצרות הפתוחות זו לזו ופתוחות לרשות הרבים. Lema davar domeh leshalosh chatzerot
hapetuchot zo lezo upetuchot lireshut harabim. This case of the three people
is just like three courtyards. מאי שנא התם דפליגיתו? Mai shna hatam
de'pligitu? Why there by the courtyards do you say that if you
don't do one big עירוב eruv for all three, everybody's got a
problem? ומאי שנא הכא דלא פליגיתו? U'mai shna hacha d'lo pligitu? And
why here do you agree that it can work that the middle
guy is okay with the two outer guys? רבנן, Rabbanan, and the
Rabbis will say back, התם... Hatam... התם אבשו דיירין hatam avshu dayarin
there there are a lot of inhabitants in the courtyard. הכא לא
אבשו דיירין hacha lo avshu dayarin here there are not a lot
of inhabitants. So what does that mean? So hold on, I just
want to check what רש"י Rashi says. Just one minute. Right. So
basically, the way רש"י Rashi says it is, look, here I can
manage that if you tell me move in this space and not
move in that space, fine, there's only three of us, I'll remember
to only go up to my עירוב. eruv. I won't accidentally, just
because you middle guy are using that space, I'm not going to
accidentally go into that space. But in the courtyard case, if you
allow this, there's so many people that live here, right? And you
know and so many people that live here that once you start
allowing people to go into here, somebody is going to forget and
wind up going, you know, and use and going into the other
courtyard and using the space of the other courtyard. So because there
are few people here, you know, there's there are not too many
moving parts to manage and you can remember where everybody can go
up to. But because here there's so many people, we can't allow
this because it'll come to then all going there and using their
using their stuff. Usually it's the opposite. Fewer people who two people
know the הלכה. I know, you know sometimes we do say if
there's a lot of people they'll remind one another. But here there's
like it's a lot of people not not working together as a
group, you know. It's a lot of people in a shared space
but with like a lot of moving parts. So therefore רש"י Rashi
says with to this case no light, because it just it's going
to lead to problematic. It's going to lead to moving כלים kelim
from the courtyard A to courtyard C and courtyard C to courtyard
A. There are just too many people involved. Okay, so let's take
a look now as we turn to this courtyard case. שתיים חיצונות
shtayim chitzonot and the two outer ones, I'll call them A and
C, cannot, you know, use one another's space. You can't take take
כלים from like A and move them into C or from C
and move them into A and so on. Now it doesn't mean,
I want to clarify that, it doesn't mean that somebody over here.
We're back to this again, as you see. By the way, back
to the diagrams. Okay. It doesn't mean that, you know, somebody from
A can't walk over to C and like use the כלים in
courtyard C. You know, if courtyard if if if they made here,
you know, I go from I don't know, from you know a
whole different street, you know, from you know a mile away, assuming
it's not a תחום problem, and come visit you in your courtyard
and I haven't made an עירוב eruv with you. Since you made
an עירוב, eruv, I can carry in your courtyard. Why not? You
made an עירוב. eruv. This is a good space. It's all one
unified רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. The problem is, what it really means
when it says A and C are problem is, I can't take
a כלי kli some type of a vessel or whatever, something that
was in the courtyard and move it from C to A or
from A to C, because the space here that's all considered to
be one unified space is the BC space. So I can't take
something from the BC space and move it into the A space
and I can't take something from the A space and move it
into the C space. So that's just to be clear what it
means. I'm allowed to go there and move the vessels that are
there, but I can't take vessels from outside of there and move
them into there. Yes. If Rashi says then you can't even have
B going to either one because B is unified with C and
with A. Right, so that's exactly what so that's essentially what the
רבנן rabbanan are saying. They're saying in the case of three people
that's exactly illustrates the point. With three people I can allow the
middle guy to be okay with the guy to his left and
the guy to his right and we're not somehow concerned because, you
know, it's not a lot of confusion. But here, and I think
it's a good point that Charlie makes, you know, what you could
wind up doing is you could take a vessel from A into
B, right? And that's allowed and use it there and then you
sort of like forget where that vessel came from and then you
wind up taking it from B into C. And that's exactly why
the rabbis say that even if in principle this is okay, we're
not going to let this work because it's more likely to be
problems than the three people case. And that's exactly what the גמרא
just said. Okay. Yes. What if you had this vessel and you
carried it from C to B right and gave it to somebody
else and then walked to A and the other that somebody else
from B carried it. Yeah, it doesn't matter which what the person
is doing. It sort of matters, you know, in terms of, yeah,
the vessel and so on. Okay, but but it's an interesting question
about what happens if it like stops in the middle, you know,
does it sort of become like a מקום פטור makom p'tur etc.
You know, so keep that in mind as we continue the גמרא.
Okay, so the גמרא says like this. Okay, so the גמרא says
שתיים חיצונות ואמאי, shtayim chitzonot vamai, why is this why is it
in this ABC case, why is it that you're actually the גמרא
is going to say it should be more lenient, it should all
be one רשות. reshut. ואמאי כיון דערבו ליה חיצונות בהדי אמצעית vamai
keivan de'erbu lei chitzonot bahadi emtzait So the גמרא says, I don't
get it. If B and C are combined and A and B
are combined, then that could all make it into one. Now it's
assuming that the עירוב, Eruv, the box of matzahs which I'll call
it, is placed in B. So if the עירוב Eruv of both
AB and BC is placed in B, right? So let's say you
have your one house here that has both עירובין, Eruvin, okay. So
if that's true, this one house represents a unified AB and a
unified BC and it's all in one house so it should be
a unified ABC, okay. It could all unify everything. So the גמרא
says, אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, כגון שנתנה אמצעית עירובה בזה
ועירובה בזה. kegon shenasna emtzo'is eruva b'zo v'eruva b'zo. The problem was,
no, AB's עירוב Eruv was put in A, and BC's עירוב Eruv
was put in C. Okay, so that's why they remain separate because
they're not brought together in B. ורב ששת אמר, V'Rav Sheshes amar,
now רב ששת Rav Sheshes says, אפילו תימא שנתנו עירובן באמצעית, afillu
teima shenasnu eruvan b'emtzo'is, even if AB and BC, the עירוב Eruv
was both in B, כגון שנתנוהו, kegon shenasnuho, we weren't going to
finish today, I knew what side B looked like, בשני בתים. bishnei
batim. It's like you put it in two houses. The problem was,
what's that? The problem was, was that you put the AB עירוב
Eruv here and you put the BC עירוב, Eruv, I mean they
could be next door to one another. So what it winds up
doing is it basically says that there is, you know, as if
everybody, AB is all, is this whole space. Let's call this guy's
house, I don't know, Fred. And we'll call this guy John. How
about Barney? So Barney. So basically what it says is, right, that
this is, it's not all Fred's space. If it was all in
Fred's house, it would all be Fred's space. But it's not all
in Fred's house. So what it basically says is that this is
Fred's space and this is John's space, and therefore it's not all
one space and that's why you've got a problem because it's in
two separate houses. Okay. כמאן, Keman, says the גמרא, according to whom
are you saying that two separate houses is a problem? כבית שמאי?
KeBeis Shammai? דתניא, we learn in a ברייתא. חמשה שגבו את עירובן,
Hamisha shegavu es eruvan, five people collected the עירוב. Eruv. Five is
just a number, you know, to indicate like many, right. Okay. All
the people in the courtyard. They collected the עירוב. Eruv. ונתנוהו בשני
כלים, V'nasnuho bishnei keilim, and they put the foods into two vessels.
בית שמאי אומרים, Beis Shammai omrim, אין עירובן עירוב, ein eruvan eruv,
it's not good, it all has to be in one vessel. ובית
הלל אומרים, u'Beis Hillel omrim, עירובן עירוב, eruvan eruv, it is good.
So we're assuming that according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, no matter
even if they could be, you know, significantly separated from one another
and considered to be one. So the גמרא makes the obvious distinction.
אפילו תימא בית הלל. Afillu teima Beis Hillel. No, this answer works
even according to בית הלל. Beis Hillel. עד כאן לא קאמרי בית
הלל התם, Ad kan lo kaamri Beis Hillel hasam, when does בית
הלל Beis Hillel say it's one? אלא בשני כלים בבית אחד, ela
bishnei keilim b'bayis echad, two vessels in one house because the whole
idea is to define everything as essentially the domain of that one
house. אבל בשני בתים לא, Aval bishnei batim lo, two separate houses
they would not say it's one עירוב, Eruv, they would say it's
separate עירובין, Eruvin, and here too basically you have a John's space
and a Fred's space and they do not get unified even if
they're both in courtyard B. Okay. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב
אויא לרב אשי. Amar lei Rav Aha brei d'Rav Avya l'Rav Ashi.
So now we understand why this works, why it isn't better that
it's all essentially B because it's not all in the same house.
And we also understand why the חכמים Chachamim disagree because it's quite
likely if you allow AB then it'll turn into an AC type
of a case and vice versa. Okay, and that's what the Rabbi
said beforehand why they didn't like it. Now we're going to say,
you know what, this really should be fine and it should be
totally one רשות reshus regardless. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב אויא
לרב אשי. Amar lei Rav Aha brei d'Rav Avya l'Rav Ashi. לרב
יהודה קשיא ולרב ששת קשיא. L'Rav Yehuda kashya u'l'Rav Sheshes kashya. Whether
רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda explanation that the עירוב Eruv was put in
A and in C, or רב ששת's Rav Sheshes explanation that it
was put in B but one in Fred's house and one in
John's house, okay, either way I have a problem and really it
should be better. It should all be fine. Why? לרב יהודה קשיא,
L'Rav Yehuda kashya, here's my question according to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
that it was put in A and in C. דאמר כגון שנתנה
אמצעית עירובה בזה ועירובה בזה, d'amar kegon shenasna emtzo'is eruva b'zo v'eruva
b'zo, that AB's עירוב Eruv was put in A and the BC
עירוב Eruv was put in C. וכיון דערבה אמצעית בהדי חיצוניתא, v'keivan
d'arva emtzo'is ba'adei hitzonita, once A and B make their עירוב Eruv
and the עירוב Eruv is put in A, הויא להו חדא, havya
lehu chada, now we have AB as a defined unit, right? AB
made an עירוב, Eruv, things have to happen sequentially in time. So
we'll imagine that AB's עירוב Eruv happened first and BC's עירוב Eruv
happened second. So AB made an עירוב, Eruv, they put their עירוב
Eruv in A, fine. Now they're one AB unit. Okay. הויא להו
חדא. havya lehu chada. Then what happens? הדר וערבה בהדי אידך, hadar
v'arva ba'adei idach, then when somebody, the people of B, all get
together and make an עירוב Eruv with C, שליחותא עבדה. shlichusa avda.
The people of B are no longer people of B. They're people
of a new country, right, it's Czech-o-slovakia, right, it's AB, right? It's
not Czech's or Slovakia. Czechoslovakia map. So, so now when B combines
with C, it's the people of Czechoslovakia, it's the people of AB,
and therefore it should define as one big עירוב eiruv together with
C. Okay, they're just doing the שליחות shlichus of their friends back
there in A. Or is it just the opposite? They didn't do
it all at the same time. That's what the גמרא is going
to answer. Okay, so A, I, so I think that way I
still don't get why it doesn't all become one big domain. רב
ששת'ס Rav Sheshes's קשיא, according to רב ששת Rav Sheshes they're in
different houses, I also have a problem. תהוי כחמישה ששרויים בחצר אחת.
tehavei kechamisha sheshruyim bechatzer achas. It could actually be worse according to
רב ששת. Rav Sheshes. Why? Imagine you had five people in one
domain, ושכח אחד מהם ולא עירב, veshachach echad mehem velo eirev, and
one guy didn't participate in the עירוב. eiruv. What's the consequence of
that? דאסרי אהדדי. de'asrei ahadadi. If one guy is left out, then,
then, then it's all a problem. It doesn't work because they, it's
not one unified domain. So he's saying according to רב ששת, Rav
Sheshes, right, I don't get it. If you had separate houses, so
basically within courtyard B, it's all Fred's domain and it's all John's
domain, right? So there are two separate רשויות reshuyos going on in
B. Well, normally, if you don't have everybody participating in one unified
רשות reshus in a חצר, chatzer, it doesn't work. The whole idea
is to unify. So in this courtyard, it should not be considered
unified at all and nobody could carry. Right. So by this opinion,
it would be a problem to have overlapping עירובים eiruvim in a
city, which used to be the case in Manhattan and the Bronx
and is today the case in Flatbush. Right. So with עירובין eiruvin
made by different synagogues. Right. So that's a very, well, okay, that's
a, hmm, that's an interesting question which I have to think about,
but that's you are right that's essentially what's being asked. While the
argument is that overlapping should be okay, the argument is no, it
should define it as two competing spaces. Yeah, it used to be
one עירוב eiruv was at Lincoln Square and the other was Sherith
Israel. Interesting. Okay, so we will so, so let's keep that in
mind as we see what the resolution to this is. Alright, so
the גמרא says like this, אמר ליה רב אשי, amar lei Rav
Ashi, so רב אשי Rav Ashi said back, לא לרב יהודה קשיא
ולא לרב ששת קשיא. lo leRav Yehuda kashya velo leRav Sheshes kashya.
It's not difficult according to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, not to רב
ששת. Rav Sheshes. Okay, לרב יהודה לא קשיא, leRav Yehuda lo kashya,
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda you wanted to say you created an AB
entity and then it was joining together with C. No. כי היכי
דאמר, ki heichi de'amar, like Michael said, כיון דעירבה אמצעית בהדי חיצונה,
keivan de'eirva emtzais bahadi chitzona, since the middle one joined together with
the outer one, ושתים חיצונות בהדי הדדי לא עירבו, ushtayim chitzonos bahadi
hadadi lo eirvu, but the outer ones did not, nobody from A
joined together with C or vice versa. So if that's true, גליא
דעתיה דבהני ניחא ליה ובהני לא ניחא ליה. galya dateih debeni nicha
lei uveni lo nicha lei. They made it clear that when B
was joining together with C, that wasn't their interest. The fact that
A sat that out and, you know, was willing to make an
עירוב eiruv with B, but sat out the BC thing made it
clear that they did not want to join together with C, so
you cannot say that when B was going with C they were
representing also A. Okay, so that doesn't bother me. Okay, they don't
become one entity for all purposes. Okay, so that's fine. Now how
about the other question? ולרב ששת לא קשיא, uleRav Sheshes lo kashya,
according to רב ששת Rav Sheshes it's not a problem. אם אמרו
דיורין להקל יאמרו דיורין להחמיר? im amru diyurin lehakeil yomru diyurin lehachmir?
Just because we're going to be lenient and basically, you know, in
order to consider it like everybody lives here and everybody lives here,
you mean להקל lehakeil is how the עירוב eiruv works, we consider
them all living in one place. So that's in order to be
lenient, but we're not going to be מחמיר and say that it's
literally as if somebody from courtyard B sat out. Nobody from courtyard
B sat out. Okay, people from the other courtyards are seen as
ex-, you know, everybody from A is now living in Fred's house
and everybody in C is now seen as living in John's house.
Okay, but the real-, that's only, you know, that's only like theoretically
in order to allow it to be defined as one domain. It's
not a reality, and the reality is that everybody that's really living
in B is participating in the עירוב eiruv and nobody is sitting
it out. Okay. Now אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav, so let's start introducing one more case just because this
wasn't confusing enough. אמר, and you see this huge תוספות there's two
major different explanations of this גמרא, I'm going to give you רש"י'ס.
Rashi's. זו דברי רבי שמעון. zu divrei Rabbi Shimon. This is the
position of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that AB works and BC works.
אבל חכמים אומרים, aval Chachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say, now before
we had the חכמים Chachamim saying something because they were concerned about
a גזירה gezeira that you'll come to accidentally go from A to
C. Here we're going to make a more principled objection to רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. What do the חכמים Chachamim say? רשות אחת משמשת
לשתי רשויות, reshus achas meshameshes lishtei reshuyos, one domain can be used
by two other domains, אבל לא שתי רשויות משמשות לרשות אחת, aval
lo shtei reshuyos meshameshos lireshus achas, but two domains cannot be serving
one domain. What does that mean? Well, that should be totally, totally
transparent, right? Which is why רש"י Rashi and תוספות have completely opposite
explanations of what it means. So what רש"י says it means is
the following. רש"י says look, here's the problem. I mean it should
have been evident clearly, רש"י'ס Rashi's explanation is quite good based on,
you know, if you were looking at this, right, it should be
clear that, you know, B should be conceptually problematic. because B is
competing רשויות *reshuyot*. You can whether you put the whether you put
the עירוב *eiruv* in Fred and John's house, you put the עירוב
*eiruv* in A and C, nevertheless there's two separate רשויות *reshuyot* going
on in B. Okay, so that's what רש״י *Rashi* says is why
the חכמים *chachamim* disagree. They say רשות אחת *reshus achas* let me
just get the language right. Okay. These two רשויות *reshuyot*, A and
C, cannot לא שתי רשויות משמשת לרשות אחת *lo shetei reshuyot mishameshet
lereshut achad*. One domain B cannot make use of both A and
of C. If it's making use of both A and of C,
it is essentially you know pulling itself in both and contradictory ways.
So B cannot carry anything into A and B cannot carry anything
into C because once it does, it basically is saying that it
has like competing alliances and it has no unity. But A can
carry into B because B can be considered like you know it
could be A is the dominant רשות *rishus* right and B is
it could be like this right? A is the dominant using B,
C is the dominant using B, there's no contradiction here. Okay, but
for B to carry from its רשות *rishus* into A or for
B to carry from its רשות *rishus* and to into C then
you have essentially this and that's a contradiction. Okay because then there
is because B is showing that it's being pulled in opposite ways
and it's not unified. So according to רש״י *Rashi* what the גמרא
*Gemara* means is רשות אחת משמשת לשתי רשויות *reshut achas mishameshet lishtei
reshuyot*. These are the שתי רשויות *shtei reshuyot*, A and C, they
can both make use of B, they can both carry into B
and make use of B, but אין שתי... so that's I'm sorry.
רשות אחת משמשת לשתי רשויות *reshut achas mishameshet lishtei reshuyot*. So oh
רשות אחת *reshut achas* is B. B can serve two רשויות *reshuyot*,
it can serve A and it can serve C, but אין שתי
רשויות משמשת לרשות אחת *ein shtei reshuyot mishameshet lereshut achad*. But C
and A cannot both serve B because if they're both serving B,
B is using both of them, then it is a contradiction being
pulled in opposite directions. So the short version being A can carry
into B, C can carry into B, but B can't carry into
the opposite ones because that's conceptually contradictory. I will just tell you
just not to confuse you more, but תוספות *Tosafos* says the exact
opposite. תוספות *Tosafos* says for practical reasons, conceptually you understand what רש״י
*Rashi* is saying, right? You understand that this is a contradiction, this
is not a conceptual contradiction, but practically תוספות *Tosafos* says the exact
opposite. If you allow A to carry into B, what might happen?
A would then carry into C. And that'll lead to bringing it
to C and C to B will lead to A. So תוספות
*Tosafos* says the opposite. B can you know B can carry into
A because it's taking it away from a problematic space, and B
can carry into C because it's taking it away from a problematic
space. But A cannot carry into B and C cannot carry into
B, the exact opposite of רש״י *Rashi*. So what's the point of
the עירוב *eiruv*? What? What's the point of the עירוב *eiruv* for
B? What? Only for B? Yeah, A and C were there. But
it's the exact opposite of רש״י *Rashi*. רש״י *Rashi* says the point
of the עירוב *eiruv* was for A and C, it didn't help
B. Okay. But anyway רש״י *Rashi* is a conceptual issue that it's
being pulled in opposite directions, תוספות *Tosafos* is a practical issue, if
we allow carrying this way it'll come to be more of a
problem. Alright, and we will so anyway we will see what the
response of this is in the tomorrow in the גמרא *Gemara*.